<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The court and city vagaries or intrigues, of both sexes. Written by one of the fair sex.</title>
            <author>One of the fair sex.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700-1710</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6584A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC N4154</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896874</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896874</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135248</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80690)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135248)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2463:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The court and city vagaries or intrigues, of both sexes. Written by one of the fair sex.</title>
                  <author>One of the fair sex.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>52p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed: and sold by J. Baker, at the Black Boy in Pater-noster-row,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1710?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Daniel Defoe.</note>
                  <note>Baker was at this address 1680-1710.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sex --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sex roles --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135248:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135248:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135248:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135248:2"/>
            <p>THE Court and City VAGARIES, OR INTRIGUES, OF BOTH SEXES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by one of the fair Sex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed: And Sold by <hi>J. Baker,</hi> at the
<hi>Black Boy</hi> in <hi>Pater-Noſter-Row.</hi> Price Six-Pence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:135248:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135248:3"/>
            <head>TO THE AUTHOR.</head>
            <p>AT laſt, my dear <hi>Idalia,</hi> I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected the fair Criminal, and found out your little wanton Frauds, in concealing a legitimate Birth of your Brain from me: But, upon ſecond Thoughts, I am ſatisfy'd your Modeſty has deny'd me the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of aſſiſting your Labour, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulating you upon ſo hopeful an Iſſue. Had I ſuſpected you ſo near your Time, I ſhould have attended the firſt Cry, and look'd upon the Offspring with all the forward and officious Sentiments of a Friend. You could have no ways defended your ſelf from a Partiality to your Cauſe, but by maintaining a Privacy. Methinks I trac'd you in every Feature; each beauteous Lineament confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the happy Mother; but ſtill I was at a Loſs. The kindly Stamp betray'd the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Original; and I was often feeling the<pb facs="tcp:135248:4"/>Goddeſs thro' the thin Drapery. You are ſo happy, my charming <hi>Idalia,</hi> in your native Charms, that you will never covet borrow'd Ornaments.</p>
            <p>There's no altering your Charms; the leaſt Manly Stroke, as it would take from the Soft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the She-Pencil, ſo it would add a diſagreeable Varniſh to the tender Colours you have laid on. The ſole Fault I find in you, is, that you have moraliz'd at an Age of innocent Liberties. It croſſes upon Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to ſee a young Philoſopher in Petticoats giving Cautions againſt Experiments, that every young Lady ſhould be in ſome Meaſure acquainted with, to guard her againſt future Inſults. Such Adventures as you repreſent in your firſt Scene, might be acted to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement, had not a diſhonourable Bully been the firſt Aggreſſor. The only Way to know the Artifices of perfidious Man, is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with them at large; and the affected Vows and Tenderneſs of that Sex, ſhould be decently known, before the regular Attacks in an honourable Way for Life. Go on, my fair Maid, in Purſuit of theſe amorous Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes; laſh the barbarous Part of our Sex, but indulge to the harmleſs Tenders of a well-natur'd Swain, and make <hi>Damon</hi> and <hi>Paſtora</hi> happy from Twenty to Thirty.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:135248:4"/>
            <head>THE Court and City Figaries OF BOTH SEXES.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <p>I SHALL begin with a remarkable Paſſage that happen'd very lately; which I hope may ſerve by Way of Caution to all young Ladies, who are induſtriouſly ſearching out the Knowledge of Ill, with a pious Deſign to avoid it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aminda</hi> and <hi>Ciladira,</hi> two very hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, well-bred, religious, young Women, of the firſt Rank in the City; I'll aſſure you, Ladies of the niceſt Reputation, which may be obſerv'd in their grave Looks and ſedate Behaviours, and I believe may juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerve the Character of Women of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. They are kept under great Reſtraints by their Parents; which, with a natural <pb n="6" facs="tcp:135248:5"/>Deſire of adding new Conqueſts to a Crowd of Admirers, has put them upon an Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of regaling themſelves in private, and, as often as Opportunity ſerves, to go in Search of Adventures, by Way of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſement; which Diverſions they have follow'd for ſome Time, with great Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, both at Home and Abroad, and never fail to return victorious. This has encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd 'em to proceed with greater Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than ever, being obſtinately opinionated of their own Conduct.</p>
               <p>Theſe Ladies are pretty often ſeen at <hi>Hide-Park,</hi> under the Cuſtody of <hi>Ciladira</hi>'s Mother; but one Day having got the Coach to themſelves, the Weather being extream pleaſant, were reſolv'd not to loſe Time and Opportunity, but gave Orders forthwith to be ſet down at a Relation's in <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> where, after a ſhort Viſit, they diſmiſs'd the Coach, with a Meſſage, that they were oblig'd to ſtay there at Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and ſhould take a Hack to come Home. They had another Excuſe as ready to the Lady of the Houſe, for taking Leave in ſuch Haſte; and accordingly make the beſt of their Way for St.
<hi>James's-Park,</hi> where they had not been long, before they had the Pleaſure to find their Beauty at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract all Eyes; and no Doubt but they heard a great many Sighs and Whiſpers, as <pb n="7" facs="tcp:135248:5"/>they mov'd thro' the gazing Crowd of Beaux that flutter'd around 'em: All which paſs'd for good Omens, tho' as yet none durſt aſſume the Courage to attack 'em. At laſt, one more daring than the reſt, draws near, keeps Pace, curiouſly ſurveys and attends their Motions. They took the Hint, views him as ſtrictly, and by his Garb, Air, and Deportment, eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd him, as they imagin'd, to be of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. He had not waited long for an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to introduce his Diſcourſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one offers it ſelf; which was, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve ſomething they were diſputing on. The Ladies being bent on a Frolick, if they lik'd the Perſon that ſhould make an Attempt, were not very hard of Acceſs, and eſpecially to ſo fine a Gentleman as this, endeavour'd to make themſelves as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and agreeable as poſſible. The Hero is ſo abſolutely charm'd with their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance and Converſation, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves himſelf no longer on Earth; <hi>Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>theſe are real Goddeſſes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from their Celeſtial Habitations, not only to dazzle the Eyes, and inflame the Hearts, but to puniſh all with Death, who have the daring Impudence to approach 'em.</hi> And being now darkiſh, claps down on his Knees, cloſes his Hands, and implores Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for his ſacrilegious Attempt. The
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135248:6"/>Girls, ſeeing themſelves thus idoliz'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to think there was ſomething in it. Immediately one fancies ſhe is <hi>Diana,</hi> and the other <hi>Pallas;</hi> but upon farther Reflex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, found they had Reaſon to confeſs themſelves meer Mortals, and ſubject to Human Frailties; as indeed it prov'd in the Concluſion. <hi>Damon</hi> was very difficult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought to believe they were ſo: But however, finding his Company did not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe, ventures from one Degree to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to come to a better Underſtanding with them. He knew the World through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or at leaſt the baſer Part; and eaſily judg'd who he had to deal with. Their Innocence and Rank, were viſible in their Perſons and Behaviours; ſo that he needs not make much Search into that, but took Opportunity, on all Occaſions, to let them underſtand his Quality, as in this Manner; <hi>We were a great many Noblemen at Dinner with the Duke of — to Day;</hi> and when any Body anſwer'd him, it was, <hi>My Lord,</hi> ſays he, <hi>or your Lordſhip may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me on all Occaſions,</hi> and ſo on, with a great many very entertaining Stories. After ſome Time ſpent thus agreeably, the Ladies were oblig'd to think of returning Home. <hi>Damon</hi> eagerly preſſes for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to hand 'em into their Coach. They anſwer'd, that was already diſmiſs'd, and <pb n="9" facs="tcp:135248:6"/>ſhould therefore ſpare him that unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Trouble. He then offers 'em his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot and Equipage that waited; and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the Victory, he declar'd <hi>Aminda</hi> had gain'd over his Heart, and that he himſelf would attend at her Chariot Wheels. This great Complement and Condeſcention, in a Perſon of this Diſtinction, ſerv'd to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe that good Opinion and Eſteem ſhe had already receiv'd of him. However, this Offer could not be accepted, for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reaſons, which he ſuffer'd himſelf to be convinc'd of; but ſtill perſiſted in his Deſign of conducting them ſafe Home, and pretended he muſt ſtep on one Side, and leave Orders with his Servants where to wait on him afterwards. He was no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er gone, but <hi>Aminda</hi> began to extol his Perſon and extraordinary Qualifications, to the higheſt Degree imaginable, and ſaid ſhe found ſo much Difference between the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of a Man of Quality, and that of a private Gentleman, that indeed ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd ſhe ſhould hardly prevail with her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hereafter, to make the latter a tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble civil Anſwer, if he ſhould ever attempt to make Love to her. Whether <hi>Ciladira</hi> had really a truer Taſte, or whether it was En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy to her Companion, becauſe he addreſs'd himſelf more particularly to her, ſaid ſhe could not believe him what he would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135248:7"/>to be; and would have continu'd on that Subject, but
<hi>Aminda</hi> would by no Means encourage ſuch diſhonourable Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions. By this Time <hi>Damon</hi> was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, and made what Haſte he could to uſher 'em into a Hackney-Coach he had provided, where they were no ſooner en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, but he began to entreat they would permit him to treat 'em with ſome Jellies, and Ice-Creams, at <hi>White</hi>'s Chocolate-houſe, The Windows being drawn up, it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to diſcover them. Theſe, with a great many other Perſwaſions, prevail'd, and the Ladies grow eaſy, and extreamly delighted; upon whieh, the Spark takes Advantage to recommend innocent Diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons above all Things, and rails at all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent old Women; who, becauſe they are paſt the Enjoyments of Life, are envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of thoſe who ought to poſſeſs 'em, and render Pleaſures as dangerous and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, with frightful <hi>Ideas,</hi> devis'd to keep Fools in Ignorance, and ſo conſequently under their Juriſdiction; but that ſo much Beauty, with all the Perfection Nature could beſtow, was not given 'em with Deſign to be bury'd in Oblivion: And to depart out of the World, juſt as they came into it, would prove to little purpoſe. Thoſe ſtrong Arguments overcame all the weak ones they could bring in Oppoſition, and <pb n="11" facs="tcp:135248:7"/>at laſt were oblig'd to yield the Debate, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to his Diſcretion for that Time, and ſuffer themſelves to be convey'd to a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern in the <hi>Hay-Market.</hi> I beg the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Pardon, for ſpeaking ſo very plain; but however, if they can keep their own Countenance, and refrain from bluſhing, it ſhall never go farther for me. After a ſplended Entertainment, and abundance of Compliments paſs'd on all Sides, it grew late, and the Ladies were very uneaſy to be going Home. He ſaid it was too early yet, deſires 'em to take off their Glaſſes with Chearfulneſs, and be thankful. This Speech gave them the firſt Allarm; but they did not know whether to take it as Jeſt or Earneſt. He goes on, and bids 'em conſider between themſelves, whether they would both or one go Home with him to his Lodgings. Upon this, they aſk'd, with a great deal of Indignation, which ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently expreſs'd their Surprize and Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what he meant, and who he took them for. He anſwers: <hi>Look ye, Ladies, ye may put on Diſguiſe, and give your ſelves what Airs you pleaſe; but at this Time ye have miſs'd your Aim. I know the World too well to be impos'd on.</hi> You'll gueſs, by this Time, <hi>Aminda</hi> began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent her Choice of a Lover, and <hi>Ciladira</hi> as much enrag'd to have her Judgment neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected,<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135248:8"/>gave her Friend a ſevere Reprimand for drawing her into the Snare, contrary to her own Inclinations, which perhaps their utmoſt Care and Politicks could not diſentangle. <hi>Aminda</hi> falls upon him with high Words, in Hopes to over-power him that Way; but finding this Stratagem fail, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> was oblig'd to alter the Scheme, and endeavour to ſooth him into good Nature. At laſt, with abundance of Difficulty, they manag'd it ſo as to quit the Houſe, but could not poſſibly get quit of the Raſcal. He was reſolv'd to purſue 'em to Deſtruction, lays violent Hands on <hi>Aminda,</hi> dragging her towards the <hi>Strand,</hi> pinching and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting her in a grievous Manner. <hi>Cila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dira</hi> purſu'd as faſt as ſhe could, and both join'd their Prayers and Entreaties in vain to this inflexible Barbarian; for all the Return they could get, was, That when he met with ſuch Jilts, he knew how to uſe 'em: That they had urg'd him to ſpend a great deal of Money, he could employ much better; and ſwore he would have Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction one Way or other, before they part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and would therefore give 'em three Things to chuſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Go and lie with him all Night, or be ſecur'd in the
<hi>Round-houſe,</hi> or elſe return all the Money he had depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited on their Accounts. <hi>Ciladira</hi> was glad to find they might have their Liberty on <pb n="13" facs="tcp:135248:8"/>this laſt Condition, and deſir'd to know how much they were indebted to him; he anſwer'd, Five Guineas. She was then at as great a Loſs as ever, knowing at that Time they had ſcarce one between 'em; but ſaid, if he would let them know where to direct, ſhe would give her Word and Honour it ſhould be ſent him next Day without fail. As this Scoundrel had no Notion of Honour, ſo it prov'd to as little Purpoſe to make him ſuch Propoſitions. He ſaw 'em well dreſs'd, and adorn'd with Jewels of conſiderable Value, eſpecially <hi>Aminda,</hi> whom he made his particular Ward; and, like a true Infernal, never ceas'd to torture and afflict, beſides tearing her fine lac'd Lappits and Ruffles all to Rags. He obſerv'd <hi>Ciladira</hi> had only a Gold Watch and Diamond Ring, which he bid her leave in his Cuſtody, 'till ſhe could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form her Promiſe; but not being willing to do this, he order'd her to pawn 'em at a Tavern in St.
<hi>Martins-Lane,</hi> where he had dragg'd them with Deſign for that
<hi>Round-houſe,</hi> if other Projects fail'd. By this Time the Watch had Notice, and were haſtening to ſecure them all; which <hi>Ciladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> prevented, by declaring their Innocence and Diſaſter in ſo moving a Manner, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a little Money to drink her Health, that ſhe prevail'd upon them to <pb n="14" facs="tcp:135248:9"/>withdraw. She runs in this Confuſion, and procur'd the Money, deliver'd it to him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, and demands her Companion, who ſtood trembling, lamenting, and almoſt dying in the Hands of her Perſecutor. He tells her they had not adjuſted all Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters yet; but for her own Part, ſince ſhe had defray'd the Expences he had been at, he was content to permit her the Freedom of going Home when ſhe pleas'd; but for this little ſaucy Jilt, he had another Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning to make with her, both for her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence, and his Loſs of Time, which ſhe muſt account for before they part. This laſt Demand ſtruck them into the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Horror and Defpair imaginable, while he redoubled his Oaths to make her a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Example. <hi>Ciladira,</hi> who has a Soul truly brave and compaſſionate, diſdaining the mean Conſiderations of Self-Preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, choſe rather to undergo thoſe preſent Inconveniencies, together with the Hazard of future Advantages, than to abandon her Friend in Diſtreſs, deſir'd to know how ſhe muſt redeem her from Bondage. Bully anſwer'd, the Thing depended on herſelf, that Diamond Croſs which hangs, as a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Addition, on her more illuſtrious Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, will pawn for ten Guineas, to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe her Liberty. <hi>Aminda</hi> was cut to the Heart, with the Apprehenſion of loſing<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135248:9"/>her belov'd Ornaments, to which ſhe is ſo extreamly bigotted, that ſhe would endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger her eternal Reputation, and ſuffer all the Puniſhment he could inflict, rather than part with any one of them. <hi>Ciladira</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Temper and Reſolution, went and engag'd her Watch, as ſhe had before her Ring, and was returning, when a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſeiz'd her in his Arms, calling her Angel and Goddeſs, with a great many ſuch Speeches. She was ready to ſwoon at the Repetition of what had betray'd her to this; but ſeeing ſome promiſing Appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in him, ſhe caſt herſelf at his Feet, and begg'd he would pity a diſtreſſed Maid. He was extreamly mov'd with her Requeſt; and looking upon her with a more different Regard than thoſe who are accuſtom'd to ſuch Diſorders, generouſly offer'd his Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance againſt all Inſults or Affronts that might be offer'd her, and that he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to protect and defend her with the laſt Drop of his Blood. This Cavalier is a Colonel in the Army, has a great deal of Honour, and real Courage, which he had ſignaliz'd on ſeveral Occaſions. <hi>Ciladira</hi> was much comforted to meet with a Knight-Errant; but however, to prevent a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, leaſt it might prove a Means to expoſe 'em, clapt the Guineas into his Hand, catch'd Hold of
<hi>Aminda,</hi> return'd him ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135248:10"/>Thanks, and ſo would have parted. No Doubt the Sharper was well ſatisfy'd with this, eſpecially when he ſaw a Gentleman who ſaid he was a near Relation, and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting ſomething more than ordinary, took Hold of his Hand, and deſir'd to know for what Reaſon he had receiv'd that Money; would have urg'd him in to drink a Bottle of Wine, and inform him how far he was oblig'd to him on the Account of thoſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. The poor Fellow, who durſt not contend with any but thoſe who could not defend themſelves, turn'd pale as Death, ſhrunk back, and only ſaid the Ladies were very welcome, bow'd, and wiſh'd it had been in his Power to have ſerv'd them far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
<hi>Ciladira</hi> was glad to let this paſs, leaſt he ſhould diſcover any Thing to their Diſadvantage, and ſaid, that the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they had to this Gentleman, were for freeing 'em from the Clamour of a Hackney Coach-man, who had impos'd a great deal more than his Due, and not having Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney enough about 'em, he had been ſo kind to lend 'em a Crown, which was what he ſaw her return him. This paſs'd pretty well on all Sides, and the Spark made off as faſt as he could, throughly glad of this Night's Succeſs. The Colonel begg'd to 'ſquire them Home, and did not fail to make abundance of Complements by the<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135248:10"/>Way, for the Honour they had done, in admitting him rather than the other: But having caſt his Eyes on
<hi>Aminda,</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving her Cloths ſo diſorder'd, and her Looks ſo ſorrowful, imagin'd ſhe had had foul Play, and with Difficulty brought
'em to confeſs their ill Uſage, tho' they care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully omitted that Part of the Story that reflects on their Conduct. He chid 'em ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely for not putting it in his Power to retrieve their Loſſes, and chaſtiſe the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain. At parting, he extreamly importun'd <hi>Ciladira</hi> to honour him with a Line or two, directed to <hi>Man</hi>'s Coffee-houſe; which ſhe promis'd to do, as a grateful Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment for the Service he had done them; and I ſuppoſe went to Bed ſufficiently mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify'd with their Adventure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>AMongſt all my Acquaintance, I never obſerv'd any ſo compleatly whimſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and remarkable of herſelf, (and is that they call ſomething ſo entirely out of the Way) as Lady <hi>Tuneal.</hi> She is a Woman of Quality, a great Pretender to Vertue, Wit, and Diſcretion, with a Mixture of Philoſophical Notions, and may with Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſtile herſelf—a Perſon—every Way diſtininguiſhable; and tho' ſhe be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135248:11"/>Man-hater, yet has nevertheleſs, thro' the Sollicitations of her Friends, been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd with to enter into a conjugal State, much to her own Diſſatisfaction; but had the good Fortune, after ſome few Years, to be releas'd from him to whom ſhe cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsly bore ſo much Averſion, and plac'd as the Center of all her Uneaſineſs and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiets. She is ſo far from playing the Hypocrite on this Account, that ſhe open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declares a Diſlike and ill Opinion of all Women, who do not agree with her Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents on the ſame Occaſion, and can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver believe, but that a Woman of Vertue will always eſteem it her greateſt Bleſſing to be freed from thoſe filthy—uſeleſs—lumbering—Male-Creatures. She has one only Daughter, Heireſs to a plentiful For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, and every Way deſerving, but I think her Ladyſhip does not ſeem to place much Joy in her, or indeed any Thing this Earth produces, excepting her moſt dearly beloved Spinet; to which ſhe is ſo entirely devoted, that ſhe thinks every Moment loſt, that is not employ'd in the Improvement of this out-of-Faſhion In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of Muſick. She not only makes in the Buſineſs of her Life; but, as tho' her future Happineſs depended thereon, ſuffers nothing to intercept; but if ſhe be oblig'd ſometimes, tho' with great Regret,<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135248:11"/>to receive what ſhe calls impertinent Viſts, ſhe is forc'd to ſit up very late, nay, often the whole Night, before ſhe can make a Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all her Tunes; which ſhe never fails to do, before ſhe ſleeps. She has a ſingular Method in every Thing ſhe ſays and does, and is attended with an Imperfection, I ſuppoſe rather habitual, than natural; which gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally proves the greateſt Hinderance to her Employment or Diverſion; that is, ſhe can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpeak of the leaſt Thing, or give any ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Orders in her Family, without Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of uſeleſs Words, and will fetch every Thing ſo very far about, that it's impoſſible to gueſs what ſhe aims to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude in. Every one of thoſe Words muſt be diſtinctly utter'd, with a Pauſe which laſts a Minute, or more, according as ſhe requires Time to ſigh and breathe in; ſo that one has loſt the Beginning of the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, before one can learn the latter End. It's not long ſince a Lady call'd on me, to wait on Lady <hi>Tuneal.</hi> We found her at her uſual Paſs-time, but in pleaſanter Temper than ordinary. She no ſooner ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd us in a Poſture of going, but ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to intreat our Stay, declar'd ſhe was never better pleas'd in Company, and that ſhe did really eſteem us as Perſons of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion; and therefore hop'd we ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with her, as to thoſe Formalities and<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135248:12"/>Decorums, which might not anſwer at this Time with her Conveniency; for having been that Day much interrupted in her Muſick, ſhould therefore be oblig'd to ſit up late, which always proves extreamly prejudicial to her Health. We beg'd her Ladyſhip to uſe us with the ſame Famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arity ſhe would her Daughter, or thoſe of her Attendance. After we had been agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably enough entertain'd for ſome Time, with ſeveral new Tunes, of which ſhe is never unprovided, at the ſet Time, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to her Cuſtom, which is as unaltera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> ſhe rings her Bell; upon which, Mrs. <hi>Smart,</hi> her Woman, deſires to know her Ladyſhip's Pleaſure. She begins, Smart,—<hi>I have call'd you with Intention—to conſult—about Supper.</hi>—Her Woman propos'd ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Things, which I thought proper for Night; but my Lady looks frighted, turns pail, and proteſts ſhe has given her the Spleen to the higheſt Degree, in naming ſuch groſs Meats at this unſeaſonable Hour, and at laſt recovers Breath to cry out,—Smart,—<hi>you are a Perſon—of a hail Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution;—but when a Perſon—has liv'd ſo long with—a Perſon of Quality,—there might be gathering up—ſome Fragments of Senſe,—at leaſt enough to—diſtinguiſh them—from the Commonalty:—But—to ſpeak yet<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135248:12"/>plainer ſtill,—tho' with abundance—of Difficulty,—for want of Breath,—as well as Loſs of Time,—which to me—is always precious,—very precious,—tho' not ſo with you,—and the unthinking World;—yet, I do ſay,—you might have diſtinguiſh'd mine—from vulgar Appetites;—have ſpar'd me all theſe Conſiderations,—and have come with—ſomething ready projected,—ſuitable to the—Delicacy of my Palate,—and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs—of Conſtitution withal,—by way of Cordial,—to revive decaying Spirits.—Smart</hi> anſwer'd her Lady, that ſhe had nam'd what ſhe knew of, to be proper in all thoſe Caſes; and that ſhe dare ſay, if the Truth were known, her Ladyſhip had her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf projected the Supper ſhe deſign'd, and only urg'd all this to try if ſhe could di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; which in all Likelihood might prove as difficult, as it was for the
<hi>South-</hi>Sayers and Magicians to tell King <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> not only the Interpretation, but the Dream too: But if ſhe would let her have her Commands in a Word, ſhe ſhould rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily be obey'd. The Lady reply'd,
<hi>Why, truly,</hi> Smart,—<hi>I have obſerv'd you to be—a Perſon—always ready furniſh'd—with a Stock of Spirits,—and ſo conſequently al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways on a Hurry;—and ſince you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce me—to the Neceſſity—of naming the Thing—my ſelf, I deſire you'll ſtep down—<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135248:13"/>into the Kitchen, and leave Orders—with the Cook—to make me—half a Porringer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of Water-Gruel.—Smart,</hi> not a little glad to receive the Meſſage, in Hopes to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs'd for that Time, was going in all Haſte to deliver it, when her Lady calls her back, with a Charge to let it be thin, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thin. She was no ſooner diſpatch'd with theſe ſecond Orders, but was again recal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to take a more ſtrict one yet, which was, that it muſt not exceed half a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringer, but rather abate ſomething of half a Porringer, and to be ſure that it be Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty-Gruel. After this, ſhe falls to ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her Fingers on the Spinet, with greater Vehemency than ever; which put her into ſuch Diſorder, that ſhe was oblig'd to deſiſt, and recover Strength, by ſighing and gaſping afreſh.
<hi>Smart</hi> finding her La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in ſuch Extremities, propos'd to have a Spoon-full of Sack in the Gruel, as a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Cordial, and might incline her to Reſt: Upon which, ſhe ſinks into her Chair, ſtruggles for new Life, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd that ſhe was abſolutely overcome on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the Name of thoſe—ſtrong—ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying—adulterated—debauch'd—Liquors. After ſhe had ſupp'd, we took our Leaves; but had the Honour to receive an Invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to dine with her the Week following; and ſaid, ſhe hop'd there was no need to <pb n="23" facs="tcp:135248:13"/>make Apologies for our not eating with her then; as being Perſons of hail Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, thoſe Evening-Refreſhments were needleſs; and made no doubt but that we had already learnt to know, that when Nature is arriv'd to its full Growth, and no viſible Signs of Decay, thoſe ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Nouriſhments ſerve not only to create or increaſe the ill Humours in the Body, but to raiſe and cheriſh ill Diſpoſitions in the Mind.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the Failings that attend this Lady, and indeed ſeveral others of our Sex, this one ſeems moſt predominant, through a miſtaken Zeal to Vertue; they make too curious Search into thoſe Things they would appear to have the greateſt Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence to; which I ſhall diſcover more particularly hereafter, and is what every truly vertuous Woman ought to overlook, and endeavour to keep herſelf in Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of; but perhaps they agree with thoſe Words Mr. <hi>Dryden</hi> makes
<hi>Lucifer</hi> ſpeak in his State of Innocence:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For to know Good, is good, and therefore fit;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And to know Ill, is good, for ſhuning it.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>No Doubt but theſe Words were very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for his Deſign, and, amongſt others of that Nature, had their deſir'd Effect; but,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135248:14"/>on the contrary, as to the latter Part, were I capable to judge or adviſe, believe it more ſafe, as much as poſſible to remain unknowing of all Things that tend to Ill.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>HAving been a little indiſpos'd the laſt Week, I had the Honour to receive Viſits from ſeveral of my Acquaintance, moſt of them being Perſons of Diſtinction and Merit, who, beſides the Pleaſure they gave me in their Converſations, has encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd me to entertain a little better Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of my ſelf than ordinary, as finding I am not wholly neglected; I mean by thoſe of my own Sex.</p>
               <p>After the firſt Complements ended, and the Ladies plac'd according to their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Degrees, Lady <hi>Quickſight</hi> broke Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; <hi>Madam,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>if it won't be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent in me to entertain your Company, I'll tell you an Obſervation I made juſt now coming through the</hi> Mall. I anſwer'd, <hi>Your Ladyſhip will lay me under a particular Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation, in doing it in a much more agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Manner than I am capable of.</hi> She made a Return I did not deſerve, and went on,
<hi>I ſuppoſe you know, or at leaſt have heard of ſuch a Gentleman,</hi> naming him, <hi>a Great Stateſman, tho' not ſo particularly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135248:14"/>addreſs'd to in this preſent Parliament, as that before the late Revolution in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. I obſerv'd him in a very penſive Mood, taking ſeveral ſhort Turns in the</hi> Park, <hi>and was as often met by a Nurſe with four or five Children, who miſs'd no Opportunity of dropping him Curtſies, but was paſs'd by a long Time diſregarded. At laſt ſhe bethought herſelf of another Stratagem, and order'd the Children ſo as to meet him in a full Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and attack him by way of Complement, while ſhe lead up the Rear. This unuſual Salutation call'd him from his politick Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations. He ſaw them very pretty, and well dreſs'd, and was extreamly pleas'd with their Manner of accoſting him. He aſk'd the Nurſe if ſhe belong'd to them, and ſaid, he never ſaw ſuch fine Children in his Life; and imagining their Parents to be conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, deſir'd to know whoſe they were. The Nurſe anſwer'd,</hi> Sir, they are your own, and live in the ſame Houſe with you. Are they ſo? <hi>ſays the Father:</hi> Indeed I did not know it, nor do I remember I ever ſaw one of them before.
<hi>But however, to let the Nurſe ſee he did not diſbelieve what ſhe told him, and that he approv'd of her Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Diſcipline, gave her a Guinea, and order'd her to take them Home. It's very ſtrange to me,</hi> continu'd Lady <hi>Quickſight, that a Gentleman, who is both a good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135248:15"/>and a good Father, and makes it his Endeavour to raiſe great Fortunes for his Children, ſhould be ſo extreamly bigotted to publick Affairs, as to remain thus ignorant of his domeſtick ones, and not know his own Children, tho' they live in the Houſe with him. Not at all,</hi> reply'd <hi>Delamine; I think it ſufficient if he knows his Wife, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes with her. I know a certain Colonel of the Guards, of City Extraction, but having a natural Inclination to what he calls Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, went two or three Campaigns into</hi> Flanders, <hi>in Purſuit of Honour, 'till he loſt that little he had; and at laſt came Home, and purchas'd the Commiſſion he is now poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd of. This Spark has a Wife and two Children, whom he has made ſuch Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to him, that he has now almoſt brought himſelf to believe there is no ſuch People in the World; and I believe ſcarce knows any one of them when he meets them; but if by Chance any of his more conſiderate Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions would be reminding him, he ſwears it's all Impoſition; and knowing the Diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages he has reduc'd them to, hopes, that he has hitherto bully'd them out of a juſt Maintenance, makes no Doubt in a little Time but to bully them out of their juſt Claim too, without giving any ſufficient Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for what he ſays or does. Certainly ſuch a Man muſt needs be eſteem'd heroick, who<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135248:15"/>can thus bravely contend, and triumph over a weak Woman and young Children, becauſe he has put it out of their Power to defend themſelves! and if he gains his Ends, I deſire we may all petition the Parliament to have him publickly acknowledg'd, and treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a victorious Conqueror. Delamine</hi> would have proceeded farther, but the whole Company unanimouſly begg'd her to lay aſide that Subject, he being the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Theme of Diſcourſe for that, or ſomething equally as ridiculous; tho' at the ſame Time all own'd he had once been a very pretty Fellow, and ſo might have continu'd, if he had not took thoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods to make himſelf deſpis'd by all the rational World. While they were thus buſy in Remarks on others, ſtriving who ſhould be moſt heard, I thought it better Manners to give Attention to, than inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept their Talk, 'till at laſt they told me I had not ſpoke two Words ſince they came into the Room. I anſwer'd, that being conſcious of my own Incapacities, together with a due Regard to thoſe who honour'd me with their Preſence, was certain I could reap much more Advantage by being a Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, than a Speaker. However, rather than give any Diſguſt by my Silence, I'll ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to draw a Cenſure of a contrary Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and for want of ſomething more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable,<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135248:16"/>ſhall tell a very odd Thing that lately happen'd to my ſelf, and is one Cauſe of my preſent Indiſpoſition. The Ladies all begg'd to hear that, and Lady <hi>Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight</hi> cry'd,
<hi>I hope you are not in Love; I never thought you inclining to that Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Not at all, Madam,</hi> ſaid I. Your Ladyſhip's much more diſcerning, than the vain Coxcomb that miſconſtructed me; tho' upon hearing my Story, perhaps you'll ſay I had as great a Share of Vanity, as he.
<hi>You muſt know here is a Gentleman come to lodge in our Neighbourhood, who takes all Opportunities to let me underſtand he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to keep a very ſtrict Survey over my Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Behaviours; ſo that I am under the greateſt Reſtraints imaginable, to find that I can't ſtir Abroad, move in my own Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or receive Company, but he muſt have immediate Information; and is ſo perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally lolling in his Window, with his Eyes fix'd here, that it's impoſſible for any Thing to ſlip his Knowledge. As to my ſelf, there is nothing worth remarking; but what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexes me, is poor</hi> Amelia. <hi>She had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to call on me for the Opera; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we don't duly frequent thoſe Places, ſhe was deſirous not to miſs any Part of the Entertainment. Having been dreſs'd in a very great Hurry, ſhe took a ſudden Whip from the Coach, to haſten me down Stairs;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135248:16"/>but had the Misfortune to drop her Shift at the Door, which hung in her Petticoats, and was deſign'd to have been left at Home: Upon which, the Spark took upon him to burſt out into a downright Laughter, tho' he did what he could to ſmother it, while her Servant took Care to deliver it into my Maid's Cuſtody. You'll gueſs, Ladies, at the Shame and Confuſion this occaſion'd us; which increas'd, when we 'ſp'd him at our Backs, as ſoon as we had taken our Places in the Theatre, where I ſuppoſe he diverted himſelf at the Expence of our Bluſhes.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melia <hi>has never been here ſince; and for my own Part, I appear as ſeldom as poſſible. And is that the only Cauſe?</hi> ſays Lady <hi>Quickſight. When you firſt began to ſpeak of your Neighbour, I apprehended ſomething more than all this.</hi> I found ſhe would pump it out, and thought it more ingenious to do it voluntarily. <hi>That is, Madam,</hi> ſaid I, <hi>what I am going to tell you: This very Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman finding me uſe all Induſtry to avoid him, and that it would continue difficult for him to ſee me any where but at Church, manag'd it ſo as to be in the ſame Pew with me every</hi> Sunday,
<hi>and always places himſelf either next, or over againſt me, inceſſantly ogling, and uſing ſeveral irreverent Geſtures, which gives me abundance of Uneaſineſs. If, to prevent being ſtar'd at, I turn my Head<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135248:17"/>on one Side, he takes Occaſion truly to daſh his Foot againſt mine, with Deſign to ſet it right again; ſo that I am oblig'd to keep my Eyes fix'd on my Fan, or look directly over him to the Parſon; which methinks gives me a very old-faſhion'd Air; for I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd Ladies of the higheſt Quality, and in the</hi> Royal Chappel
<hi>it ſelf, don't throw away a Look, or miſemploy a Thought that Way, but are at full Liberty to compare Jewels, receive and entertain one another with as much Freedom, and as great an Air of Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry, as in the Drawing-Room, or a Ball at Court. The only Refuge I have under theſe Reſtraints, is kneeling; but I'll aſſure you, my Spark is more a Gentleman, and better bred, than to kneel at Church, or ſhew the leaſt Devotion; tho' at the ſame Time I dare ſay he would not think it beneath him to adore and proſtrate himſelf at the Feet of an inſignificaut Mortal, in Hopes by ſuch Means, to draw her to her Ruin, while per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he is only deſpis'd and laugh'd at; which indeed is the juſt Reward of ſuch En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours. When I am to riſe, he is offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly offering his Hand, and by that Means gains Opportunity to ſqueeze mine; and, in ſhort, has made all the Advances imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; ſo that it were impoſſible for me to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him otherwiſe than a Lover, tho' he had not ſpoke one Word yet; but that paſs'd for<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135248:17"/>want of Aſſurance, and I ever expected when he would gain Courage enough to make a Declaration of his Paſſion; not that I had the leaſt Inclination to accept his Propoſals, tho' he has a pretty Eſtate, and conſiderable Place under the Government; yet there is no Inchantments lodg'd in his Perſon, ſo as to make him amiable in my Eyes. Howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, I did not know but he might expect I ſhould take it an Honour; and becauſe I would not ſeem to leſſen his Deſerts, or va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue my own without Cauſe, I ſtudy'd a long Time for an Anſwer to that imaginary Letter he might ſend me, and contriv'd it ſo as he could not think me imperious or fantaſtical, or that my Refuſal was meant in Affront to him, I thought it beſt to ſay, that a Senſe of my own Imperfections had occaſion'd me to vow Celibacy ſome Time ſince, as knowing I am unworthy to be belov'd. This Letter lay by me ſo long, that I began to deſpair of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver having Uſe for it, and grew a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd, leaſt the Product of my Studies ſhould be loſt: But one Evening I had Notice, that the Gentleman's Foot-man over the way had brought a Letter, and would deliver it only to my ſelf. Upon firſt hearing, I confeſs I was in twenty Minds, whether to ſend this I had by me, or not: At laſt, I found it would be a conſiderable Time before I could accompliſh another, and that I had no more
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135248:18"/>to do with this, but to ſeal and direct it, and by that Means gain the Reputation of a Woman of a quick Thought. I took his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſaid I would ſtep up and read it, and ſend down an Anſwer immediately. The Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low told me very briſkly, it did not require an Anſwer, and was gone before I could ſay another Word. I ſuppoſe he had given thoſe Orders, becauſe he was reſolv'd to take no Denial; ſo retir'd into my Cloſet, and to my Aſtoniſhment read this:</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Madam,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>IT's with infinite Regret I have prevail'd with my ſelf to diſcloſe a Secret, that I with Reaſon fear will cauſe you much Uneaſineſs; and withal to give you this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome Caution; that is, for your own Sake, I beg you'll endeavour to ſuppreſs your growing Paſſion for me, which has been apparently manifeſt by thoſe Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings and Emotions which naturally ſeize you at my Approach, and I with ſo much Pleaſure have diſcern'd: But have the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, Madam, to be engag'd in an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair my Friends put me upon, before I had the Honour to know of you. It's a juſt Conſideration of your Merit, that won't ſuffer me to let you languiſh under a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Expectation of what may never be in my Power to gratify. I hope you are ſo<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135248:18"/>good a Chriſtian, as to bear this Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment patiently, and be aſſur'd, that tho' I cannot, yet there is nothing in the World I covet more, than to be</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Entirely Yours.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was a long Time before I could recover from the Surprize this Letter had thrown me into, and was really griev'd to find, that one can't bluſh for a Fellow's Impudence, but he muſt miſinterpret it to Love. At firſt I was in the Mind to write, and undeceive the Puppy; but upon Conſideration, found I ſhould but leſſen my ſelf, and increaſe his Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, by ſhewing any Regard to it; for the only Way to mortify ſuch Animals, is to ſcorn and neglect them, and to let the Fool ſee it was not in his Power to cauſe me the leaſt Uneaſineſs. The next Day, being</hi> Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, <hi>I dreſs'd my ſelf in the beſt Cloaths I have, and went to Church with a gayer Air than ordinary; where I had not been long, before I had the Pleaſure to find my Oppoſite had met with a greater Diſappointment than my ſelf, and could have laugh'd at his Folly, if I had thought it worth while; but to do Juſtice on both Sides, I can't ſay I eſcap'd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unpuniſh'd for my Pride; for in leaving off my Hood that Day, the Weather being grown cool, I got a very great Cold,<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135248:19"/>which occaſions me to keep my Chamber at this Time.</hi> The Ladies fell a laughing at my Amour; and by this Time I ſuppoſe were pretty well tir'd, and took their Leaves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>I Shall not undertake to give a circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Account of the unhappy Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences that aroſe not long after the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, between Sir
<hi>Bounce Sparkit</hi> and his Lady: Tho' her Vertue, Beauty, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Merit, were his chief Inducements to enter into the matrimonial State; yet, through the Inſtigations of his pretended Friends, and her Enemies, he ſoon grew to an Indifference, and afterwards to a Neglect, or rather ill Ufage, of the only Perſon in the World that entirely loves, and maintains an inviolable Fidelity to him. Sir <hi>Bounce</hi> is one of thoſe who pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces his whole Felicity in himſelf, and does not require the Additions a good Wife is capable of giving, to make his Life eaſy to him; and as he never takes nor gives Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for any Thing, he thought fit not long ſince to withdraw to a ſeparate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, and devote himſelf up to Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantries; while his forſaken Spouſe has full Leiſure to lament her Unhappineſs,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135248:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>or Time and Opportunity, if ſhe pleaſes, to revenge her Injuries; tho' I believe ſhe never entertain'd a Thought of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but on the contrary, has made it her utmoſt Endeavours, if poſſible, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve her Huſband's fleeting Paſſion: In order to which, ſhe went one Morning to his Chamber, where ſhe found him equip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping in a riding Habit, and with all the Sweetneſs in her Looks, and moſt obliging Terms imaginable, ſaid ſhe was come to Breakfaſt with him, and to have the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of an Hour's Converſation, if he would permit it. He anſwer'd with a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry haughty Air, that ſhe had made Choice of a wrong Time to gain any of his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, being in Expectation every Moment of a Gentleman to call of him for <hi>Hide-Park;</hi> and that if ſhe would ſhew him any Marks of her Duty and Prudence, ſhe muſt immediately retire. The Lady began to be a little inrag'd at her cold Reception, and his Ingratitude; and briſkly told him, thoſe Cautions were needleſs, and that ſhe wiſh'd he would acquit his Duty, as well as ſhe had done her's: Upon this, Sir
<hi>Bounce</hi> commanded her not to talk; but ſhe ſtill diſobeying, he order'd his Valet to lead her to her own Apartment. This Indignity was reſented to the laſt Degree; and ſhe did not fail to tell him at parting,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135248:20"/>
                  <hi>It is not long ſince you would have gone down on both Knees, to have obtain'd the Bleſſing your ſelf.</hi> Under this new Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, ſhe flies to <hi>Olympa,</hi> a young Lady, her near Relation and Confident, who lives with her in the Houſe. It's to her only ſhe opens all her Grievances. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympa</hi> always endeavours to rally her, out of her Melancholy, and tells her, a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's Love is not worth preſerving; and as ſhe is a true Coquet, declares ſhe can never value any Man farther, than to have the Glory of a Conqueſt; of which ſhe is ſo extreamly covetous, that ſhe can't bear the Thoughts of a Cavalier, who is not her profeſs'd Adorer; and never fails to play the Tyrant, after ſhe has once gain'd a Captive. She will needs have Lady <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kit</hi> Abroad to divert her; and being in the Morning, and not in an Humour to dreſs, they walk'd in Diſſabil, to make Choice of ſome Things they had Occaſion for at a Miliner's in the <hi>Pall-Mall;</hi> where, after they had been ſome Time, were returning Home to Dinner, when <hi>Olympa,</hi> whoſe Eyes are always open to gay Appearances, 'ſpy'd a fine young Gentleman with his Head laid down to ſleep in a Tavern Window; the Saſh being up, and another ſtanding by with a Whip under his Arm. Upon which, ſhe cry'd, <hi>Look, my Dear, do you know ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135248:20"/>of thoſe pretty Fellows?</hi> Lady <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kit</hi> immediately recollected ſhe ſaw her Huſband put on that fine lac'd Coat to ride out in the Morning, and that this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was the Friend he expected ſhould call of him; ſo concluded they were now come back, and would dine there together. While her Thoughts were thus employ'd, he that ſtood, gave the other a Pluck, who ſoon wak'd, look'd upon them, and ſmil'd. They both ſaw very plain, at that Time, it was Sir <hi>Bounce</hi> himſelf; and his Lady was not a little reviv'd at the pleaſant Look he had given her, and began to think it was not impoſſible but that his Mind might now change, as much as it had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. But however, leaſt her too curious Obſervation might give any Umbrage, ſhe was going in all Haſte; but <hi>Olympa</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an Inclination to look back, ſaw him beckon, and make all the Signs he could to have them ſtop, 'till he was ready to throw himſelf out of the Window. She was extreamly pleas'd with his ſeeming Eagerneſs to join Companies, and had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready doom'd the Stranger her Slave. She tells Lady <hi>Sparkit,</hi> that ſhe is confident Sir <hi>Bounce</hi> is grown impatient to come to a Reconciliation; and becauſe ſhe would not ſeem to have any Deſigns, tells her, ſhe has now a fair Opportunity to cloſe<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135248:21"/>with her Happineſs; which, if loſt, may never be retriev'd; and that as it is her Huſband who makes this preſſing Invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhe ought not to ſtand upon Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rums, or raiſe any Objections againſt the Decency of the Place; eſpecially ſince ſhe knew him to be a Man of that Temper whom nothing can oblige, but an entire Obedience and Reſignation to his Will and Pleaſure, tho' it appear never ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable to the World. Lady <hi>Sparkit</hi> was very inclinable to comply with thoſe Reaſonings, but again fear'd his Deſigns might not be ſo well, perhaps, as they at firſt imagin'd. While ſhe remain'd thus dubious, and ſlowly moving homewards, <hi>Philaret,</hi> which was the young Stranger, purſu'd and overtook them, who only bow'd, and offer'd her his Hand to lead them back, without ſaying one Word. She aſk'd why Mr.
<hi>Sparkit</hi> would not rather come himſelf? He anſwer'd, <hi>Madam, I very difficultly prevail'd upon him to permit me the Honour.</hi> By the Way, ſhe proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to aſk him ſeveral Queſtions concerning the
<hi>Park,</hi> and if they had brought any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Company with them. To all which he anſwer'd very <hi>Appropo.</hi> When they were come to the Tavern, ſhe ſaw four or five ſtrange Foot-men ſtand with their Hats off; but thoſe ſhe imagin'd might belong<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135248:21"/>to the Gallant who was
'ſquiring her up Stairs, while <hi>Olympa</hi> follow'd. They had not quite aſcended, before the other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman came running to meet them; and
<hi>Philaret</hi> call'd out, <hi>My Lord</hi> Newlove, <hi>if you were ſenſible of the Bleſſing, you would fly to aſſiſt me in uſbering up theſe Ladies.</hi> Upon this, they immediately found their Miſtake, but too late. <hi>Olympa</hi> run down as faſt as ſhe could; but Lady <hi>Sparkit</hi> not having Liberty to get away, clapt hold of the Baniſters, and fell into a Swoon. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they had brought her into the Room, they did not fail to uſe their utmoſt Care and Diligence to bring her to Life, which was effected in a little Time; but upon finding herſelf in the Arms of him ſhe had miſtook for her Huſband, ſhe was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fall into a Relapſe, had they not convinc'd her by their Behaviours and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn Proteſtations, ſhe ſhould remain in their Company with as much Safety, on all Accounts, as with the neareſt Relation ſhe had in the World. But all this would not ſatisfy the diſappointed Lady; ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats, with the greateſt Urgency imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, to have her Liberty; while they, with an unreſiſting Air, and moſt profound Reſpect, ſollicit her Stay. By this Time <hi>Olympa</hi> had recover'd her Fright, and was return'd, to make Enquiry of her Friend.<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135248:22"/>
                  <hi>Philaret</hi> had Notice of it, and with abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Arguments and Aſſurances, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd upon her to honour them with her Company; which ſhe did, in Reſpect to the other Lady. Lord <hi>Newlove</hi> was ſo enamour'd with the Beauty, graceful Mein, and modeſt Carriage of Lady <hi>Sparkit,</hi> whom he ſtil'd his deſtin'd Charmer, ſent from the Gods to take Poſſeſſion of a Heart unconquer'd; and that he ſhould eſteem himſelf the moſt fortunate Man on Earth, if ſhe would permit him to devote it eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to her Service. Lady <hi>Sparkit</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd theſe Addreſſes with all the Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Neglect that's natural to a Mind prepoſſeſt; and tho' ſhe had no other Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to her Huſband, than that of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, yet ſhe found her Vertue a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Guard againſt the moſt powerful Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults. Lord <hi>Newlove</hi> is a young Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, truly heroick, and grac'd with all the Additions of Art and Nature, which can conſpire to make him irreſiſtable; and has ſo peculiar a Method in making Love, which inſenſibly ſteals upon the Hearts of thoſe preſent, as well as the Perſon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd to; and never fails to make her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy'd, tho' it were by a Siſter, or Boſom-Friend. In the mean Time, <hi>Philaret,</hi> who is no leſs deſerving, a Relation, and ſworn Brother to Lord <hi>Newlove,</hi> entertain'd <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympa</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:135248:22"/>with all the Reſpect and good Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners which becomes a Cavalier to a fine young Lady; yet, tho' ſhe is very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, he did not find himſelf abſolutely in Love with her, but kept his Eyes and Thoughts fix'd on Lady <hi>Sparkit,</hi> who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways proves moſt attracting to the real Judges of Perfections. On the other Hand,
<hi>Olympa</hi> made him ſuitable Returns, and was ſo tranſported between the Charms ſhe ſaw in Lord <hi>Newlove,</hi> and that of a Rival's Rage and Reſentment, that ſhe had not Leiſure to mind the cool Application
<hi>Philaret</hi> made to her, which ſeem'd rather through Reſtraint, than Inclination: A Treatment ſhe had never been accuſtom'd to, and what was directly contrary to the Sentiments ſhe had of herſelf; but finds now, to her great Anxiety, it was not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to love, even where ſhe is likely to continue diſregarded; the greateſt Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification that can befal a Coquet. As theſe two Lovers ſympathize in all Things, ſo their Thoughts were equally employ'd on Stratagems to ſucceed in this new A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, with that Eagerneſs to perſiſt, which is always obſervable in a beginning Flame, both fancying he had the juſter Claim, 'till they had quite forgot the Intent of their coming thither, which was to dine with two honeſt Fellows, who had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135248:23"/>the Fatigues of a Camp ſome Years; one of which was come off with the Loſs of an Eye and an Arm, whom they had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidentally met in <hi>Hide-Park,</hi> from whence they were juſt return'd when the Ladies firſt ſaw them, and had already beſpoke the Dinner. But now the appointed Time being come, the Brothers of the Blade had diſpatch'd their Affairs, and were arm'd: Upon which, they ruſh'd into the Room in a moſt ſurprizing Manner; the firſt made but one Step up to Lady <hi>Sparkit,</hi> clapt his Hat under his Arm, and cry'd, <hi>My Lord, give me Leave to kiſs your Girl;</hi> while the lame one accoſted <hi>Olympa</hi> in as familiar a Way. The Ladies being unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with thoſe Sort of Salutations, were aſtoniſh'd at their Manner of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and were ready to die with the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions they receiv'd of them. Lord <hi>Newlove</hi> ſoon perceiv'd it, and with a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming Anger, in Regard to the Ladies Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, gave Camper a fevere Reprimand for his Inſolence, tho' with that Caution as not to put their Reputations in his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by a Diſcovery who they were, but gave them all honourable Aſſurances of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and Fidelity. By this Time Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was come upon the Table, which was with all Magnificence the Place would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of. It was in vain for the Ladies to<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135248:23"/>think of diſengaging themſelves, but on the contrary, were oblig'd to be as ſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble as they could. While the Courtiers were employ'd in officiating, and ſilently admiring, the Soldiers were entertaining the Company with an Account of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Diſcipline, and beg'd they might be permitted to regale them with their marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Muſick; which was refus'd. After Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Lord <hi>Newlove</hi> and <hi>Philaret</hi> approach'd Lady <hi>Sparkit,</hi> with all the Awe and Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration they would a Deity, from whom they expect their immediate Fate; all which ſhe modeſtly evaded; while Camper plac'd his Batteries at <hi>Olympae,</hi> and after ſeveral vigorous Aſſaults, which prov'd ineffectual, he was conſtrain'd to raiſe the Siege: Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which, they both retir'd; ſo that <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laret,</hi> in Point of Breeding to
<hi>Olympa,</hi> is oblig'd to reſign to his powerful Rival, and give him Opportunity for all the Advances that is poſſible for ſuch an Aſſailant to gain over a Heart that can't remain wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible of his Merits; where, in ſpite of all her Vertue and Reaſon, he ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd, as to obtain her Conſent for a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Meeting; which, though innocently meant, had the Misfortune to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard by <hi>Philaret</hi> and
<hi>Olympa,</hi> who look'd upon this Adventure to be a Conſpiracy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her univerſal Empire; and tho' be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135248:24"/>this unlucky Accident, ſhe dearly lov'd Lady <hi>Sparkit,</hi> yet, in the Height of Rage and Reſentment, ſhe is ready to ſacrifice her to her Revenge, it being entirely in her Power, as ſhe beſt knows the true Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of her Huſband's Indifference; and that if ſhe fail'd of her deſir'd Succeſs in an Attempt projected, ſhe is already aſſur'd of having him her Vaſſal, whenever ſhe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to command it, tho' the Affection ſhe bore to her Couſin, had hitherto prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her taking any Advantages of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but always endeavour'd to conceal it from her Knowledge, that it might not cauſe her any Diſquietude. Lady <hi>Sparkit</hi> is now deſirous to be gone, when Lord <hi>Newlove,</hi> who is ſo tranſported with the Hopes of future Happineſs, is ready to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey her harſheſt Commands; and together with <hi>Philaret,</hi> conducted them ſo far as they would permit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <p>IT's about three or four Months ſince a very worthy Gentleman, a Member of Parliament, had Occaſion to be at a Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wig-maker's Shop in the
<hi>Strand,</hi> where he chanc'd to 'ſpy a fine young Lady alight out of a
<hi>Hackney-</hi>Coach from a very handſome Gentleman, to make a Viſit to an intimate<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135248:24"/>Friend of her's, a Country Lady that lodg'd at the next Houſe; he ſeeing her walk up Stairs, follow'd by her Foot-man, who carry'd ſeveral Parcels ſhe had been buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and came there with Deſign to have her Friend's Advice in the making up the Cloths for her Marriage, which was to be celebrated the Week following with that young Cavalier who conducted her thither. <hi>Mirtilla,</hi> which was the Country Lady, would needs recommend one <hi>Vainly,</hi> a fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Mantoa-woman that lodg'd up two Pair of Stairs in the ſame Houſe, and who had made it her Buſineſs to inſinuate herſelf into her Favour, to make the Cloths; which
<hi>Clarinda</hi> willingly aſſented to, and gave her Directions accordingly. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to our grave Stateſman, whom we left in the adjoining Shop, full of Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionon the late Angelick Viſion. He finds himſelf all on a Sudden plung'd into a Paſſion he had never yet experienc'd, at leaſt to ſuch a Degree, tho almoſt arriv'd to the Age of Fifty; but ſince he is ſo tranſported with Love, is reſolv'd to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify himſelf on any Term whatſoever. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly conſider'd on Propoſals of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying her with all imaginable Speed; if his Perſon be not the moſt amiable, yet his other Qualifications, with the Additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a great Eſtate, and Title of Sir<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135248:25"/>
                  <hi>J—,</hi> he knew were great Inducements to a prudent young Lady, eſpecially if ſhe had no great Fortune, as he wiſh'd, to make his Addreſs the eaſier, and begins to think on no Objection, unleſs that beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Adonis</hi> that came Home with her, as he imagin'd, might prove to be a Lover: But on ſecond Thought, fancy'd ſo much Reſemblance in their Faces, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes them Brother and Siſter; ſo ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to aſk any other Queſtions than what's the Lady's Name that lodges next Door, he was anſwer'd <hi>Vainly,</hi> the People not knowing of any other in that Houſe. This was enough for the haſty Lover. He im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately flies into his Chariot, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of going to the Play or Coffee-houſes, gives Orders to go Home, where he ſpent the Remainder of that Day and Night in contriving the propereſt Means to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce his Paſſion. Sometimes he is ready to go and throw himſelf at her Feet; but again conſiders, that being wholly a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſuch an Action might ſeem too raſh and ſurprizing; and at laſt concludes on writing firſt, to beg Leave to wait on her; which he did next Morning in the ſofteſt Terms that could be. He acquaints her with his Name, his Rank, his Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and above all, his mighty Love and indefatigable Reſolutions to obtain her for<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135248:25"/>his Wife; is impatient to know when he may be admitted to kiſs her Hand; and concludes himſelf the moſt ſubmiſſive, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Slave, that ever Beauty made ſo. This was directed for Madam <hi>Vainly</hi> at her Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, diſpatch'd away in all Haſte, and was accordingly deliver'd with a great deal of Ceremony. You may ſuppoſe <hi>Vainly</hi> receiv'd all this very civilly, and return'd the Complement as well as ſhe could, with her moſt humble Service; and that if he pleas'd to take the Pains to come there next Day at Six in the Evening, ſhe would do herſelf the Honour to attend him. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was Woman ſo pleaſingly ſurpriz'd as ſhe, at this welcome Letter. She perus'd it over and over, and fancies every Thing in her Praiſe, to be ſubſtantial Truths; but upon conſulting her Looking-Glaſs more than ordinary, finds herſelf altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther irreſiſtable, and is ready to fly into a Paſſion at the reſt of the ſtupify'd World, that could not diſtinguiſh her Charms in ſix and thirty Years Time. She now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to conſider her Admirer; and tho' ſhe never ſaw him in her Life, yet is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly in Love with him for ſeveral Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. His Quality, Eſtate, and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Intentions to make her great, are pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Motives; but yet adores him more, if poſſible, for his penetrating Judgment.<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135248:26"/>The Title of Ladyſhip, tranſports her to the laſt Degree. She concludes every Thing done, and is the happieſt Woman in the World, in her own Imaginations. She grows eager for the Pleaſure of relating her Conqueſt, and fixes on
<hi>Mirtilla</hi> as the propereſt Confident and Adviſer in this Affair.
<hi>Mirtilla</hi> was ſomewhat amaz'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve me, at the Gentleman's Choice; but however, being a very well-meaning Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Lady, was mightily pleas'd at her Neighbour's good Fortune, in Hopes to have a merry Bout at this Wedding too. She offers her Apartment to receive him, if ſhe likes it better than her own; which was willingly accepted by <hi>Vainly,</hi> who em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd all her Time in making that, and herſelf fit to entertain ſo conſiderable a Lover; but <hi>Clarinda,</hi> who had really the greateſt Share in the whole Matter, was ignorant of all that paſs'd, and came very innocently next Day to viſit <hi>Mirtilla,</hi> and enquire if her Wedding-Cloths were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt finiſh'd, becauſe ſhe had now few Days to turn in. She had no ſooner enter'd the Houſe, but ſhe found the Face of all Things chang'd, only <hi>Mirtilla</hi> was much the ſame Woman as before; but <hi>Vainly</hi> was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely transform'd into another Creature. She had juſt been adorning herſelf to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an eternal Conqueſt; ſate playing her
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135248:26"/>Fan with the awful Air of ſome great La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-Viſiter, now and then tuning up her muſical Voice to the ſofteſt Words ſhe could think on. <hi>Clarinda</hi> was ſtruck all on a Heap in her Thoughts, at this ſudden Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration; but ſeeing <hi>Vainly</hi> look ſo very ſtately, ſhe could not take Courage to aſk any Queſtion, nor durſt ſo much as name the Work ſhe expected to have ſeen done. <hi>Mirtilla</hi> obſerving her Look ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd and ſtudious, was as much in Pain to have the telling of News, as the other was to hear it; ſo makes an Excuſe to call her into the next Room, where ſhe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded the Myſtery. <hi>Clarinda</hi> could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe at firſt Hearing; but <hi>Mirtilla</hi> aſſerts the Truth with, yea verily, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed. This happen'd as <hi>Vainly</hi> wiſh'd; for ſhe was often upon the Point of bringing of it out herſelf; but deferr'd, in Hopes <hi>Mirtilla</hi> would ſave her the Labour. They were no ſooner come to her again, but ſhe begins to return her Thanks; for tho'
<hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinda</hi> was a Stranger at preſent, yet ſhe ſaid ſhe was much pleas'd with her Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and had no Affairs ſhe deſir'd might be made a Secret to her, and hop'd they ſhould be better acquainted hereafter; for truly ſhe ſhould very often beg their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies in her Coach to
<hi>Hide-Park;</hi> but indeed ſhe has ſo many Things to do and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135248:27"/>think on, that ſhe does not know at which End to begin; and as they are both going to enter into the ſame Circumſtances, ſhe ſays they muſt endeavour to aſſiſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make the beſt Uſe of their Time. She will needs have <hi>Clarinda</hi>'s Cloths ſent away juſt then to the Mantoa-woman ſhe deſigns to honour with her Wedding-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and tells her, that in Return, ſhe muſt make it Part of her Employment to enquire out amongſt her Acquaintance for a Lady's Woman, that underſtands herſelf and her Buſineſs throughly, and knows how to keep due Diſtance; for ſhe is ſure ſhe can never bear a familiar Wretch. But now the Time of Expectation draws near; the Ladies are better bred, than to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting; ſo take Leave together to ſpend the Evening at
<hi>Clarinda</hi>'s Lodgings. They had not been gone half an Hour, before a fine Chariot and Equipage, with a much more fine Gentleman, ſtopt at the Door. <hi>Vainly</hi> knew it could be nothing leſs than her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorer; runs in all Maſte to meet him at the Stairs. After the uſual Complements to a Woman of her Appearance, he deſir'd to know if Mrs. <hi>Vainly</hi> were at Home: She told him Yes; and that her Name was ſo. He ſuppoſing her to be the Mother, ſaid it was the young Lady he meant, who had done him the Honour to return ſuch and <pb n="51" facs="tcp:135248:27"/>ſuch an Anſwer, upon his taking the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to write to her the Day before. She aſſur'd him ſhe was the very Perſon he meant; that there was no other of the Name in that Houſe; and for farther Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, takes the Letter out of her Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom. He then begg'd ten thouſand Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, ſaid he was miſtaken in the Name; for that Letter was meant to another La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy about ſuch an Age, had ſuch Hair, Eyes, and every Features; and proceeded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe her very Dreſs; yet all this was not enough to convince <hi>Vainly:</hi> She did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be ſo tantaliz'd. She affirm'd ſhe was not above Eighteen, had juſt ſuch Eyes; and that if he will but come up to the Light, he will find her every Ways as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable, if not exceed the other he talks of: But, alas! it was not in the Power of all her Charms and Rhetorick, to draw him one Inch farther. Poor <hi>Vainly</hi> was perfectly confounded at this unexpected Treatment, and Labour loſt; and what between Grief, Pride, and Reſentment, was ready to break out into loud Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and offer'd to detain him by Force; which oblig'd the miſtaken Lover to take very abrupt Leave, extreamly perplex'd at the Diſappointment; but not without Hopes that a little more Caution and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, may at laſt bring him to the real <pb n="52" facs="tcp:135248:28"/>Object of his Admiration: But I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <hi>Vainly</hi> came pretty even with him afterwards; which I'll refer to ſome other Paper, when I am better inform'd of that Part of the Story.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:135248:28"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135248:29"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135248:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
